Music and mood. Music has charms to soothe the savage breast. Even centuries ago, people
knew music could change their moods. Generally, loud music makes us feel powerful, soft melodies
are calming, and happy beats make our feet move and our faces smile. Now, we're figuring
out why. Scientists have found that music affects how the brain produces the chemical
dopamine. Dopamine is associated with pleasure. When we listen to music we like, our brains
make more dopamine. The chemical makes us feel good. Even just thinking about listening
to a song we love can get the dopamine flowing. In a strange way, this suggests that music
can be slightly addictive. Researchers at McGill University studied how music affects us. First,
they measured how people's bodies responded to music. They found that when people listen
to music they like, their heart, pulse, and breathing rates change. Sometimes they feel
chills. These changes also happen when people feel strong emotions. Since dopamine is connected
with emotions, the McGill team guessed that music would cause the production of dopamine.
To test their theory, they asked eight music lovers to bring in some of their favorite
songs. After the participants had listened to the music for a while, the team injected
them with a substance that would go to the parts of the brain that collect dopamine.
If those parts were already full of dopamine, the substance would have nowhere to go. Sure
enough, the participants' brains were already flooded with dopamine. To be sure, they tested
them again the next day, but with music participants didn't like. That time, the substance did
flow to the dopamine collectors because participants' brains hadn't made dopamine. Even early humans
knew how to play good music for a pick-me-up. Now we know why.